Guide to the Abraham Goldwasser papers 1970-1997
Abraham Goldwasser papers
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives, Cornell University Library
Abraham Goldwasser papers, 1970-1997
6036/078
Goldwasser, Abraham; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union; Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees
1.5 linear ft.
Articles, reprints, pamphlets, correspondence, photographs.
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives, Cornell University Library
Papers of Abe Goldwasser, documenting his work with the ILGWU New York Cloak Joint Board and the Union Health Center of the ILGWU and UNITE.
ILGWU ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
Founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States, the ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. In 1995, the ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU) to form the Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE).
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Abraham Goldwasser was born in 1944 in Uzbekistan, USSR. After the end of World War II, the Goldwasser family returned to Poland, leaving for Paris in 1957. In 1961, the Goldwassers emigrated to the United Sates settling in Baltimore, with the assistance of HIAS (Hebrew Immigrant Aid Society). He was raised by his parents in the spirit of the Jewish Labor Bund. After graduating from high school in 1963, Goldwasser moved to New York City and attended City College of New York. In 1967, Goldwasser became a member of the Young People's Socialist League. In 1970, Goldwasser married Ettie, daughter of ILGWU Vice President, Henoch Mendelsund.
After graduating from college in 1969 and until 1997, Goldwasser worked in various positions for the ILGWU and UNITE. He was a clerk at the New York Cloak Joint Board (1969-1970), staff member of the Health and Welfare Department (1970-1972), supervisor of the Circulation Department, which was responsible for the distribution of Justice to ILGWU members (1972-1973), office manager of the New York Cloak Joint Board (1974-1977), and supervisor of the Dues Department of the New York Joint Board, created through the merger of the Cloak Joint Board, Dress Joint Board, and the Raincoat Makers Local 20 (1977-1978).
From 1977 to 1997, Goldwasser worked at the Union Health Center in New York City. At first he was as the supervisor of the Appointment/Reception Department (1978-1983). During this time he participated in the conversion of the appointment system from semi manual to computerized and creation of the beginning of a patient information system using a mini-computer.
As the supervisor of the Computer Operation Department (1983-1997), he was responsible for the entire data processing of the Health Center including, appointments, computerized patient and medical information systems, and services billing. During this period, hundreds of members visited the Union Health Center every day. In the 90's, Goldwasser participated in the discussions leading to the move of the Health Center to other floors, and a new computerized system.
After the ILGWU's merger with ACTWU in 1995, Goldwasser left the Union Health Center. Since 1997, he has been employed at Teamsters Local 237.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
The collection documents Abraham Goldwasser's work for the ILGWU's Circulation Department, New York Cloak Joint Board, and the Union Health Center (UHC). Included in the records documenting the New York Joint Board is material on the health and welfare fund, rules and regulations, and correspondence.
Goldwasser's records from the Union Health Center include reports of the Union Sanatorium Association and administrative records for Center including financial reports, job descriptions, and office memos. Also contained in the records are reports, presentations and studies, and various publications, the majority of which are related to group insurance and pension plans, health and welfare benefits, death benefits, and retirement. Information on the retirement fund encompasses the national retirement fund, the ILGWU staff retirement plan, as well as the United Health Center staff retirement plan, and the material documents comparisons, rules and regulations, summary descriptions, and financials of the pension plans. A large component of the collection concerns the documentation of the UHC's automation project of the 1980s. Records include the UHC research regarding computerization of the laboratory reports, implementation of automation, batch data processing, procedures, and patient appointment scheduling manuals. Much of the documents support the recommendation and planning for a new automation system for the center.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Goldv?aser, Avraham, -- 1919-; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union.; Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees.
Form and Genre Terms:
Papers
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
RELATED MATERIALS
Related Collections:
5780: ILGWU records
5780/060: ILGWU. Union Health Center records
5780/171: ILGWU. Union Health Center publications
SERIES LIST
Series I. Circulation Department, 1973
Series II. New York Cloak Joint Board, 1972-1977
Series III. Union Health Center,
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Circulation Department, 1973
  - Circulation Department. Manual, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series II. New York Cloak Joint Board, 1972-1977
  - New York Cloak Joint Board. Health and Welfare Fund rules and regulations, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Copy 1
  - New York Cloak Joint Board. Health and Welfare Fund rules and regulations, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Copy 2
  - New York Cloak Joint Board. Health and Welfare Fund rules and regulations amendments, 1972-1976 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - New York Cloak Joint Board, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series III. Union Health Center
  - Automation Project, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Automation [Folder 1 of 3] (Box 1, Folder 7)
    1980s
  - Automation [Folder 2 of 3] (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Automation [Folder 3 of 3] (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Automation Project Recommendation and Plan [Folder 1 of 2], 1996 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Automation Project Recommendation and Plan [Folder 2 of 2], 1996 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Finance Department report, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    5-May
  - Job descriptions, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Medical billing system (Box 1, Folder 14)
    n.d.
  - Memoranda, 1983-1988 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Memoranda, 1990-1994 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Memoranda, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Memoranda, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Memoranda, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Memoranda, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Memoranda, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Miscellany (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - National Retirement Fund manuals, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - "Planning for Tomorrow": Setting the Scope of Work for the ILGWU Union Health Center, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    4-May-95
  - Presentation to the New York Union Health Center, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    February 29, 1996, prepared by Leader Data Processing
  - Publications (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Publications (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Retirement plans, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Comparison of Union Health Center and ILGWU retirement plans, 1982-1992 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - ILGWU Staff Retirement Fund plan, 1976-1985 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Union Health Center staff retirement plan, 1976-1984 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Union Health Center staff retirement plan, 1985-1994 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Union Health Center staff retirement plan, 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Union Health Ceter staff retirement plan, retirment committee, 1986-1993 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Union Health Center staff retirement plan, report on financial statements, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Union Health Center staff retirement plan, report on financial statements, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Union Health Center staff retirement plan, financial statements, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Union Health Center staff retirement plan, financial statements, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Union Health Center staff retirement plan, financial statements, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Union Health Center staff retirement plan, financial statements, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Statistics, 1986-1997 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Studies and reports [Folder 1 of 2], 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Studies and reports [Folder 2 of 2], 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Union Sanatorium Association, annual board report, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Union Sanatorium Association, annual board report, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Union Sanatorium Association, board report, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    27-Jun-96
  - Union Sanatorium Association, Board of Directords meeting, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    5-May-97
  - CLOSED (Box 2, Folder 7)